A Finding Aid to the John White Alexander Papers, 1775-1968, bulk 1870-1915, in the Archives of American Art AAA.alexjohn
Archives of American Art
- Associations and Memberships, circa 1897-1918; Series 3; 2 Folders Box 1
  This series contains membership certificates, cards, circulars, rosters, and other records associated with European and American art organizations in which Alexander participated, or which solicited his participation. Organizations represented in this series include the American Academy of Arts and Letters, the American Academy in Rome, the National Academy of Design, the Onteora Club (New York), the Royal Academy of Fine Arts (Munich, Germany), the Ministère de L'Instruction Publique et des Beaux-Arts, the Union Internationale des Beaux Arts et des Lettres, and the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
  Items in this series are arranged chronologically. This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Associations and Memberships, circa 1897-1918; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 71-72)
- Legal and Financial Records, 1775; 1896-1923; Series 4; 5 Folders Box 1
  This series includes an 18th century road report, copyright forms, a contract, royalty statements, and receipts. Among receipts are insurance payments, membership dues, and financial transactions. Scattered receipts are also found among Correspondence.
  Additional records documenting Alexander's artwork are found in Notes and Writings.
  - Virginia Road Report Signed by a John Alexander, 1775 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Copyright Forms for Library of Congress Murals, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Contract for Carnegie Institute Murals, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Royalties of the Detroit Publishing Company, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, circa 1906-1917 (Box 1, Folder 77)
- Notes and Writings, circa 1875-1943; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  This series contains notes, essays, speeches, short stories, news articles, poems, and records of artwork written by John White Alexander, his wife Elizabeth Alexander, and others.
  Notes appear to be fragments of essays or speeches, typed and handwritten. A few rough sketches are found among the notes. Speeches by John White Alexander are mainly on art subjects. These include a 1901 talk for New York City's founder's Day entitled "Our Tariff on Art," and a 1912 address to the Onteora Club on the formation of the School Art League.
  Short stories by Elizabeth Alexander are found in typescript and handwritten form. Tear sheets for several of her published stories illustrated by John White Alexander are also found. Original drawings of some of these illustrations are found in Artwork.
  Articles about Alexander include typescripts of two critical essays by his contemporaries Sadakichi Hartmann and Anne Webb Kamaghan, a catalog description by Julia deWolf Addision, and a collection of transcribed news stories and editorials about his resignation from the Society of American Painters in Paris.
  Records of artwork include two bound volumes with information about paintings and many lists of paintings related to exhibitions and storage. The second folder of lists appears to be related to a memorial exhibitions held for Alexander in 1916, and the fourth contains a small notebook with the heading "List of Portraits and Paintings by Alexander painted before 1887."
  - Notes, undated; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 78-79)
  - Speeches by John White Alexander, circa 1901-1912; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 80-84)
  - Short Stories by Elizabeth Alexander, undated; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Short Stories by Elizabeth Alexander, Tear Sheets of Published Stories with Illustrations by John White Alexander, 1896-1897 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Essays and Speeches by Elizabeth Alexander, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Articles about John White Alexander, 1900-1901; undated; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Poems Removed from Sketchbook, circa 1875 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Poems Written for and to John White Alexander, circa 1897-1912 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Registers of Paintings and Exhibitions, circa 1887-1913; (2 volumes in 2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Lists of Paintings, circa 1893-1943; (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 12-15)
- Awards and Memorials, circa 1870-1944; Series 6; 0.8 Linear feet Box 2, OV 24
  This series contains award certificates and medals awarded to Alexander during his lifetime, and memorial resolutions and projects carried out after his death in 1915.
  Award certificates and medals are found from the Royal Academy of Art in Munich, the Carnegie Institute, and the Panama Pacific Exposition. Additional medals awarded for Alexander's artwork are found from the Societé National des Beaux-Arts, the Paris Exposition of 1900, the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, the Pan American Exposition, the Saint Louis Exposition, the Buenos Aires Exposition, and the School Arts League. Additional medals from civic organizations are also found.
  Extensive materials are found documenting the creation of the Alexander Memorial Studio at the McDowell Colony in New Hampshire, including published reports of the McDowell Club and Colony, images in the form of photo postcards and engravings, and a studio book containing photographs of the studio's construction, a history of the studio, and the signatures of resident artists. Notes and correspondence concerning the history of the studio are found tucked in the book.
  Over a dozen memorial resolutions issued upon Alexander's death by arts organizations to which he contributed during his lifetime are found. Several of these resolutions exist in ornate, calligraphic, bound volumes.
  Additional photographs of the Alexander Memorial Studio are found in Photographs. This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Award Certificates, circa 1878-1915 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Oversized items housed in OV 24
  - Medals, circa 1870-1922; (20 items in 3 shoe boxes) (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Blueprint of Alexander's Tomb, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Alexander Fund and Studio at MacDowell Colony (Box 2)
    - Reports, circa 1915-1926 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Images, circa 1910-1944 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Studio Book, circa 1925-1941 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Memorial Resolutions, circa 1915; (5 folders; oversized items housed in OV 24) (Box 2, Folder 25-29)
  - Commemorative Lecture by Edwin Blashfield, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Oversized Award Certificates, circa 1878-1915 (Box 24 (OV))
    Items scanned with Box 2, f16
  - Oversized Blueprint of Alexander's Tomb, 1915 (Box 24 (OV))
    Item scanned with Box 2, f21
  - Oversized Memorial Resolution, circa 1915 (Box 24 (OV))
    Item scanned with Box 2, f25
- Artwork, circa 1875-1915; Series 7; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, 14-16, OV 23
  This series contains 13 sketchbooks, sketches and drawings on loose paper, and reproductions of John White Alexander's artwork in a variety of print media, including fine prints by various printmakers. An engraved portrait of Alexander by Arthur G. Learned is also found at the end of the series.
  Sketchbooks contain drawings, sketches, cartoons, and illustrations in pencil, ink, wash, and gouache. A few are dated in the original. Others have been assigned dates during processing based on their content: cartoons and illustrations are dated to Alexander's main period of newspaper and magazine work (1873-1899), and sketches related to murals are dated to the murals' years of execution (Library of Congress, 1896; Carnegie Institute, 1905-1908). Additional notes on sketchbook content are found in the folder listing.
  Loose sketches are filed by media, including charcoal, pencil, wash, and ink. Most of the pencil sketches are preliminary studies of allegorical figures and appear to relate to mural projects. Wash and ink drawings are more finished in appearance and were executed on Bristol board, and may have been published illustrations.
  Reproductions of artwork consist of halftone prints, etchings, and engravings of Alexander's cartoons, paintings, murals, and illustrations. Reproductions are found on loose pages and in two oversized volumes. Many of the reproductions are fine prints and are signed by the printmaker. Names include George Bartle, John William Evans, Thomas Heard, William Fowler Hopson, Thomas Johnson, Frederick Juengling, W.H. Morse, Caroline A. Powell, Harry Elliott Sylvester, John H.E. Whitney, and Henry Wolf.
  The second volume of reproductions also contains other types of materials, including six photographs of artwork, one sketched caricature of Alexander dated 1885, and five photographs picturing Alexander around 1903 to 1913. Among the loose reproductions are two large color prints are signed by Alexander, and installation views of the 1915 memorial exhibition at Arden Galleries.
  Additional sketches and illustrated letters are found in Correspondence and Notes and Writings series, and additional art reproductions are found in Scrapbooks and Photographs. This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1873-1899; (3 folders; oversized items housed in box 14) (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
    (sketchbooks contain primarily cartoons and illustrations and are dated to Alexander's main years of newspaper and magazine work)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1880-1881 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    (inscribed July 1880; contains sketches from life; also contains sketches of illustrations depicting African Americans)
  - Sketchbook, 1884 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    (travel sketchbook with dated sketches, one of which is labeled "Tangier")
  - Sketchbook, circa 1891 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    (cover reads "B. Alexander, 1891"; may have belonged to Elizabeth Alexander, who went by the name Betsy or Bessie; contains seascapes, figures and a page of text)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1896; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    (contain pencil sketches of figures, landscapes, and several lunettes that appear to be related to Alexander's Library of Congress murals, executed 1896)
  - Sketchbook, circa 1905-1908 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Oversized items housed in Box 14
    (among the work in this volume are sketches from Alexander's murals at the Carnegie Institute, Pittsburgh, executed 1905-1908)
  - Sketchbooks, undated; (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 7-10)
    (five undated volumes containing a variety of work in pencil, wash, gouache, and ink; two volumes were purchased in Europe.)
  - Charcoal Sketch, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Pencil Sketches, circa 1896-1909; (5 folders; oversized items housed in OV 23) (Box 3, Folder 12-16)
    (loose sketches in these folders are mainly of allegorical figures; many are recognizable from Alexander's murals at the Carnegie Institute, Pittsburgh, executed 1905-1908; a few cartoons are found; folders are dated to the period of Alexander's mural projects)
  - Wash and Ink Drawings, circa 1873-1899 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    (contains a series of maritime scenes in wash and gouache on Bristol board, and a single figure in period costume; assuming these are illustrations, they are dated to Alexander's main period of illustration.)
  - Etchings, Engravings, and Reproductions of Artwork (Box 3)
    - Bound Volume 1, circa 1886-1894 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Oversized items housed in Box 15
    - Items Removed from Bound Volume 1, circa 1886-1894 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Bound Volume 2, circa 1885-1996 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Oversized items housed in Box 16, sol
    - Loose Items, circa 1886-1915; (4 folders; oversized items housed in OV 23) (Box 3, Folder 21-24)
  - Etched Portrait of John White Alexander by A.G. Learned, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Oversized items housed in OV 23
  - Oversized Sketchbooks, circa 1873-1908; (Items scanned with Box 2, folders 31-32 and Box 3, folder 6) (Box 14 (sol))
  - Bound Volume 1 of Art Reproductions, circa 1896-1909 (Box 15 (sol))
    Items scanned with Box 3, folder 18
  - Bound Volume 2 of Art Reproductions, circa 1886-1894 (Box 16 (sol))
    Items scanned with Box 3, folder 20
  - Oversized Sketch, circa 1885-1896 (Box 23 (OV))
    Item scanned with box 3, f12
  - Oversized Etchings, Engravings, and Reproductions of Artwork, Loose Items, circa 1886-1915 (Box 23 (OV))
    Items scanned with Box 3, folder 21
  - Oversized Etched Portrait of Alexander by A.G. Learned, undated (Box 23 (OV))
    Item scanned with Box 3, f25
- Scrapbooks, circa 1877-1915; Series 8; 1.8 Linear feet Boxes 17-22
  Eight scrapbooks date primarily from 1888 to 1915, with some earlier clippings in the first volume from Alexander's first trip to Europe in the late 1870s. Scrapbooks begin shortly after his marriage to Elizabeth Alexander and contain annotations that appear to be in her handwriting. Thus, the scrapbooks may have been created by her.
  Most of the contents of the scrapbooks are newspaper and magazine clippings, with articles about Alexander's art activities and reproductions of his paintings. Also found are scattered letters from patrons and organizations announcing honors and thanking Alexander for commissioned portraits. Other types of items in the scrapbooks include exhibition invitations and catalogs, invitations to club events, programs for speaking engagements, and a few photographs.
  Exhibition catalogs in the scrapbooks include Alexander's one-man show at Durand-Ruel Galleries (1901-1902), Pratt Institute (1905), the National Arts Club retrospective (1909), the Albright Knox gallery retrospective (1909), and the Art Institute of Chicago (1913). Other special contents of individual scrapbooks are noted in the folder listing.
  Contents of scrapbooks are in loose chronological order, with each volume covering three to five years. Scattered items fall outside of the date ranges indicated for each volume. Additional volumes containing art reproductions, engravings, and photographs are found in the artwork series. Additional exhibition catalogs and clippings are found in the Printed Materials series.
  - Scrapbook, circa 1877-1895 (Box 17 (sol), Folder 1)
    (contains 1893 letter from Puvis de Chavannes re: membership in the Societe Nationale des Beaux-Arts, 1896 letter from Prince Eugene of Sweeden and Norway inviting Alexander to exhibit)
  - Scrapbook, 1895-1900 (Box 17 (sol), Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1900-1904 (Box 18 (sol), Folder 1)
    (contains photograph of the jury of Etchings and Engravings, Paris Exposition, 1900, on which Alexander served; 1901 letter from Emile Loubet, president of France, and a notice of the same year of his honor of Crois de Chevalier de L'Ordre Nationale de la Legion d'Honneur; 1904 letter from Edward Coates awarding him the Gold Medal of Honor by the Pennsylvania Academy)
  - Scrapbook, 1904-1907 (Box 18 (sol), Folder 2)
    (contains letters from Henry van Dyke, V. van Syckel, Jane Potter Russell, Walter Gunnison, and K.M., possibly Katherine Mackay; also, telegram from JWA to EA informing her of the Carnegie mural contract for $175,000)
  - Scrapbook, 1907-1909 (Box 19 (sol), Folder 1)
    (Contains program for MacDowell club event with tableaux by Alexander; extensive publicity for the Carnegie Institute murals; and a 1908 note from H. W. Mabie)
  - Scrapbook, 1909-1911 (Box 20 (sol), Folder 1)
    (contains letter from George A. Hearn; programs and publicity for Maude Adams productions of John of Arc and Chanticler)
  - Scrapbook, 1910-1913 (Box 21 (sol), Folder 1)
    (contains note from Florence Levy re: honors from the School Art League; letter from Robert Underwood Johnson re: membership in the American Academy of Arts and Letters; 1912 photograph of the Pittsburgh International Jury, of which Alexander was a member; an invitation to a dinner honoring Alexander Drake, reproducing a cartoon by Alexander)
  - Scrapbook, 1914-1915 (Box 22 (sol), Folder 1)
    (contains annotations related to publicity over Alexander's failure to complete the Carnegie murals)
- Printed Materials, circa 1891-1945; Series 9; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 3-4, OV 23
  This series contains magazine and newspaper clippings, exhibition catalogs, circulars, bulletins, reports, books, pamphlets, and brochures.
  Clippings in this series are often duplicated in Scrapbooks, especially those dating to Alexander's lifetime. Later clippings are unique to this series. The scope of subjects found in this series is also greater, including not only stories about Alexander's career, but also about other artists, family matters, and Elizabeth Alexander's career before and after her husband's death.
  Exhibition catalogs are found for Alexander's solo exhibitions, before and after his death. Scattered catalogs for other artists' exhibitions are also found. The 1905 catalog of a Pratt Institute exhibition contains prices, and a 1915 catalog for his memorial exhibition is marked with scattered corrections and sales. Additional exhibition catalogs are found in Scrapbooks.
  Circulars include an unsigned, printed letter of protest to the Metropolitan Museum of Art related to an exhibition of European modernists. Entire issues of a variety of magazines are found, several of which contain major articles related to Alexander and his artwork. See details in the folder listing. Bulletins and reports relate to organizations in which Alexander was involved or exhibited. Miscellaneous printed materials include calling cards, a magazine subscription, and a civil defense poster.
  Additional printed materials are found throughout the collection, especially in Artwork and Scrapbooks. See series descriptions for more details. The bulk of this series has been scanned. Items not scanned include newspaper and magazine clippings, and for some published items, only the covers have been scanned.
  - Magazine Clippings, circa 1896-1922; (2 folders; oversized items housed in OV 23; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 26-27)
  - Newspaper Clippings, undated; (3 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 28-30)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1900-1914; (8 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 31-38)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1915; (10 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 39-48)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1916; (3 of 12 folders; not scanned) (Box 3, Folder 49-51)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1916; (9 of 12 folders; not scanned) (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1917-1918; (7 folders; not scanned) (Box 4, Folder 10-16)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1924-1940 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    not scanned
  - Exhibition Catalogs, undated; 1902-1905 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1915-1918; (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 19-21)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1937-1945; (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 22-24)
  - Exhibition Poster and Wall Text, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Circulars, circa 1908, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Memorial Essay by William Laurel Harris, circa 1915 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Magazines, circa 1914-1933; (6 folders) (Box 4, Folder 28-33)
    (Articles include "A Visit to Mr. Alexander's Summer Studio," by Elbert F. Baldwin (page proof); "Is Our Art Distinctively American," by JWA in Century, various obituaries and memorials; "The JWA Murals" in Carnegie Magazine; "The Portrait Work of John W. Alexander" by John V. Sears)
  - Bulletins, 1913; 1937 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    (School Art League, Mint Museum of Art)
  - Reports (Box 4)
    - Société Royale Des Beaux-Arts (Brussels, Belgium), 1908; 1911 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - New York City Improvement Commission, 1907 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Books (Box 4)
    - Autobiography of Worthington Whittridge, after 1941 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - American Academy of Arts and Letters Book of Record, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Smithsonian Institution National Gallery of Art, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Pamphlets, Brochures, and Mailings, 1926; undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials, circa 1891-1945 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    Oversized item housed in OV 23
  - Oversized Magazine Clippings, circa 1896-1922 (Box 23 (OV))
  - Oversized Exhibition Poster and Wall Text, undated (Box 23 (OV))
    Items scanned with Box 4, f25
  - Oversized Miscellaneous Printed Materials, circa 1891-1945 (Box 23 (OV))
    Item scanned with Box 4, f41
- Photographs, circa 1870-1915; Series 10; 4.2 Linear feet Boxes 4-8, MGP 1-2, OV 25-43, RD 44-45
  This series contains photographs of John White Alexander, friends and associates, family members, studios, places, exhibitions, and works of art.
  Dozens of formal portraits are found depicting Alexander, many taken by notable photographers, including Zaida Ben-Yusuf, Aimé Dupont, Curtis Bell, Elizabeth Buehrmann, and several signed Miss Huggins, who may have been Estelle Huntington Huggins, a New York painter and photographer. Also found are photographs made in the well-known studios of Pach, Sarony, and George Rockwood. Portraits of others include Alexander's friends William Merritt Chase and Edward Austin Abbey.
  Groups portraits depict Carnegie Founders' Day, the Metro Club, and the National Academy of Design. Juries include the Carnegie International Exhibition, the National Academy of Design, and one group identified as both the Academy jury and the last meeting of the Paris Society of American Artists.
  Annotations are found throughout the series, in what appears to be either John White Alexander's or Elizabeth Alexander's handwriting. Mrs. Alexander's annotations in particular sometimes contradict information found in the photograph itself, or on other photographs of the same subjects. Contradictory annotations are particularly common among jury, studio, and personal photographs, and photographs of works of art.
  Photographs of Alexander's studios include spaces in New York City; Paris; Sea Bright, New Jersey; and Onteora, New York; Alexander is pictured in some of the studios. Also found are photographs of the Alexander Memorial Studio built at the MacDowell Colony in New Hampshire after Alexander's death, several of which were taken by photographer Jesse Tarbox Beals. See Awards and Memorials for more images and documentation of the MacDowell studio.
  Individuals identified in personal photographs include Alexander, Katherine Beatty, Ed Moran, Thomas S. Clarke, and Alexander's son, James. Also pictured here is Alexander with portraits painted at the Cowan residence in Scotland circa 1900, and Alexander in a mummy costume circa 1903-1904. Numerous photographs of unidentified children appear to have been taken in Alexander's Paris studio. Photographs of Polling, Bavaria show scenic views and architectural details.
  Photographs of works of art span Alexander's career and are sometimes annotated with titles, dates of execution, and often owners. Note that annotations are sometimes contradictory. Photographs of paintings are arranged in broad chronological groups, with approximate dates noted in parentheses in the folder listing. These dates have not been verified, however, and many paintings are undated.
  Original glass negatives are found for several personal photographs, photographs of studios, and photographs of works of art. Several of the negatives of works of art are retouched and numbered in the original. Recent prints have been made from the original negatives are filed along with vintage prints. Note that recent prints of paintings have been cropped to the picture frame and do not show the negative images in their entirety.
  Additional photographs are found in Awards and Memorials, Artwork, and Scrapbooks. The bulk of this series has been scanned. Items not scanned include photographs of artwork, and duplicate photographs. Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
  - Portraits of John White Alexander (Box 4)
    - Photographs by Curtis Bell, circa 1900-1915 (Box 4, Folder 42)
      Oversized items housed in OV 25
    - Photographs by Curtis Bell, Copies, circa 1900-1915 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      Not scanned
    - Photographs by Zaida Ben-Yusuf, circa 1900-1915 (Box 4, Folder 44)